<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on two discourses concerning the divinity of our Saviour, written by Monsieur Lamoth in French, and done into English written to J.S.</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1508B</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355731</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">205939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1750:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on two discourses concerning the divinity of our Saviour, written by Monsieur Lamoth in French, and done into English written to J.S.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
                  <author>E. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year MDCXCIII [1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Stephen Nye by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Postscript", p. 22-24, is signed: E.E.</note>
                  <note>This item also appears as part of A Second collection of tracts ... London, 1693 (Wing S2267, at reel 1269:1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lamothe, Claude Grostête de, 1647-1713.</term>
               <term>Smith, John, fl. 1673-1680.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205939:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205939:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS ON TWO DISCOURSES CONCERNING The Divinity of our Saviour: Written by Monſieur LAMOTH in <hi>French,</hi> and done into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Written to <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:205939:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205939:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>REFLECTIONS</hi> on two Diſcourſes concerning the Divinity of our Saviour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AMong our other Oppoſers, we are at length attacked by the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and Monſieur <hi>Lamoth,</hi> an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Demagogue of the <hi>French</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath publiſhed two of his late Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations againſt us.</p>
            <p>I know not whether he was choſen to, or put himſelf upon the Imployment; but I will allow, that a more fit Perſon cannot be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily found for the Work by him undertaken. He hath Art and Addreſs enough; and ſuch a Degree of Confidence, as to be above both <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Fear.</hi> If he had either of thoſe, in any Degree, left to him, he would never have ſaid as he does at <hi>pag.</hi> 15, 16, 17, 34. that <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>had not common Senſe,</hi> nor <hi>any tolerable Degree of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> nay was <hi>a Mad-man,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>the Apoſtles were Blaſphemers;</hi> if we do not grant that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Trinity and of the Divinity of our Saviour, as they are now held, are true. Concerning all the Writers of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, he pronounces at once, as here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; <hi>I make no Difficulty</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>p. 33.) to aſſert, they have deceived us moſt ſhamefully, and their Writings are no better than continual Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, if Christ be not true God.</hi> As to the Chriſtian Religion, he ſaith at <hi>p. 18. It hath nothing in it that is great and ſublime, if you take from it the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not to be doubted, that in his next he will tell us, our Saviour himſelf was an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor, to ſpeak of himſelf as he did, if he were the Great Prophet only. But in the mean time, I ſhall tell him, that 'tis ill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nay 'tis unchriſtian and impious, to ſet the Perſons of the Apoſtles, and the Holy Scriptures themſelves, on the ſame Level with the litigated controverted, (<hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) doubtful and uncertain Doctrines,</hi> of this or the other Party of Chriſtians; ſo that both muſt ſtand or fall together: for 'tis to equal in their Authority our private Interpretations of the Word, with the Word it ſelf. The latter will have its true Value allowed to it, by all wiſe and good Men, while the other (private Interpretations or Opinions) ſhall even among <hi>ſuch,</hi> undergo various Changes, be believed in ſome Ages, and rejected in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; which (all learned Men know) has been the Fortune of the Doctrines, in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between us and the Church.</p>
            <p>But Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi> is heartily troubled; that, <hi>if you take away the Divinity of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, we ſhall find our Religion to contain nothing that is GREAT or S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIME,</hi> p. 18. The Socinians, on the contrary, judg, that the Deſign of Religion being (confeſſedly) this, <hi>to direct our Converſation and Manners,</hi> 'tis no Matter how plain and obvious it is; and that <hi>it</hi> being intended for the Unlearned and Vulgar, as well as for others, there was a Neceſſity, it ſhould neither be <hi>ſublime</hi> nor <hi>great.</hi> We are well ſatisfied with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter that <hi>Moſes</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> give of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>'Tis not in Heaven, or beyond the Sea, or in the Deep,</hi> (as who ſhould ſay, 'tis neither ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime nor myſterious) <hi>but 'tis in thy Mouth and Heart, that thou mayſt do it.</hi> As if he had ſaid, 'Tis an eaſy intelligible thing, congennit and connate to every Man; that none may ſay 'twas <hi>ſublime,</hi> and he underſtood it not, 'twas <hi>great,</hi> and he could not graſp it. This is the Deſcription that <hi>Moſes</hi> makes of <hi>true</hi> Religion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205939:3"/> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 12. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> repeating his Words, applies them to the Goſpel, <hi>This is the Word of Faith</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that we preach,</hi> Rom. 10. 8. But Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> and his Party are not for ſuch a Religion, they muſt have a Religion that is <hi>great and ſublime;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly they have contrived to themſelves ſuch a Religion, a Religion of which they not only ſay, but profeſs and boaſt, that 'tis <hi>above and beyond all Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You require of me, Sir, that I ſhould exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Defence that Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi> hath made of <hi>the great and ſublime</hi> Religion; I will do ſo in the following Method:</p>
            <p n="1">1. I will make ſhort Remarks on the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Arguments diſperſed up and down in his <hi>two Diſcourſes,</hi> as his Tranſlator has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented him, though he ſhould have ſaid his <hi>two Declamations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I will give an Account of the Texts, which (whether they will or no) he hath impreſſed to ſerve his Cauſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On his general Arguments.</head>
               <p>I Omit that he is pleaſed to call us, <hi>p. 52, 55, 62, 63. Enemies of Jeſus, the Profane, Innovators, Adverſaries of the Lord Jeſus, near Neighbours to Irreligion:</hi> for theſe are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements that ſome Preachers readily beſtow on as many as differ from them. Though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when he is in the Mood, (as at <hi>p.</hi> 62.) he confeſſes, that <hi>we ſeem to be innocent Lambs:</hi> and that in our Writings are found <hi>glittering Notions, and ingenious Explications.</hi> We won't thank him for the Acknowledgments which Truth it ſelf has extorted from him; nor will I reſent much his ill Language to us: but I will endeavour to treat him, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſharply, yet in a more Gentleman-like way.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 52, 53, 54. <q>By denying the Divinity of our Saviour we make <hi>the Bible the ſtrangeſt Book in the World.</hi>—The Old Teſtament will ſcarcely have the leaſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the New; we find <hi>nothing but Thwartings and Contradictions between them.</hi>—This once ſuppoſed (<hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſt is not the moſt High God) 'tis evident, that Chriſt came not to fulfil the Law and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but <hi>utterly to confound and deſtroy them.</hi> Let us ſpeak only of the New Teſtament:—What a Book ſhall we have of it, if Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt be not God?—The New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is full of antient Oracles (<hi>he meaneth of Quotations out of the Old Teſtament</hi>) to the Honour of the Living God: but 'tis as clear as the Noon-day, that the Applications that the Apoſtles make of them are <hi>mere childiſh Triflings and Blaſphemies,</hi> if our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our by one of his Natures be not the Living God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwards, at <hi>p.</hi> 53, 54. he proceeds to tell us, how the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to have ſpoken,</hi> if Jeſus Chriſt be not God. For if he is God, the Holy Spirit (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Author) has been as faulty and as blaſphemous as the very new Teſtament and the Apoſtles are. Let us hear what he ſaith; <q>Why, ſay the Socinians, might not the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſpeak magnificently of <hi>that</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, to whom we are ſo vaſtly obliged, and whom Providence has raiſed to ſuch a Degree of Glory? For that Reaſon ſay I (<hi>I Monſieur</hi> C. G. Lamoth) the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ought to have ſpoke with more Reſervedneſs</hi> of the Glory of Chriſt. The greater he is, the more is the Danger of his being taken for God; his very Greatneſs makes us the more ſtand in need of Preſervatives.—If he had not been God, the Exceſs of our Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him <hi>ſhould have obliged the Holy Ghost not to ſpeak of him:</hi> Or at leaſt, ſeeing it was not poſſible to teach his Doctrine without ſpeaking of his Perſon, to make uſe of ſuch Expreſſions as might make it evident, that he is not God. It was neceſſary, in moſt expreſs Terms, and on ſeveral Occaſions, to tell Men, this Jeſus, whom you worſhip, is not God for all that.—Neither can any thing be ſaid in the Caſe, (<hi>he meaneth,</hi> that the Holy Ghoſt has not ſpoke as Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> here directs) but only this, that the Holy Ghoſt was willing to deceive us.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205939:3"/>
               <p>Hold, <hi>Jehu;</hi> leſt inſtead of hearing that <hi>thou driveſt furiouſly;</hi> they call to thee, that thou driveſt <hi>madly.</hi> Declamations did I call theſe Sermons; they are <hi>Debacchations:</hi> For I will affirm, that no Example or Inſtance can be given of a bold and heady Writer, who hitherto ever durſt exalt his Opinion, or the Opinion of his Party, above the Apoſtles, the Scriptures, and the Holy Ghoſt it ſelf; ſo that if the <hi>former</hi> were not allowed or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be true, the <hi>other</hi> muſt be mere Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies, Blaſphemers and Fools.</p>
               <p>If the hundred and fifty Sects, or more, into which Chriſtianity is divided, ſhould all fall to ſcribling, and ſhould be as extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant in their Imputations on the Bible, as this Frenchman has dared to be, what would become of the Chriſtian Religion? It would be turned into Ridicule, by all that heard us, magnifying <hi>ſo much</hi> our own Gloſſes, Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or Opinions, and regarding the Text it ſelf, and the Authors of it <hi>ſo little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our preſent Author's Book is vouched or licenſed by two French Miniſters, who tell us, that being appointed by the reſt of their Brethren to read it, they find it entirely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the conſtant Doctrine of the French Proteſtants. I will not believe them, though they gave it upon Oath; for it never was the Doctrine of the French Proteſtants, nor of any Proteſtants, no nor of any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that if their Creed be not true, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were <hi>Mad-men,</hi> the Scriptures <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt knew not how <hi>to ſpeak as he ought;</hi> which are Words often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by Mr. <hi>Lamoth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you will ſay, Sir, but Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> has perhaps ſome particular and eſpecial Grounds for his unuſual Confidence; he hath advanced ſomething that is wholly new, and very forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in behalf of the Doctrines of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and our Saviour's Divinity. Nothing leſs, I aſſure you; you may meet with <hi>as much</hi> in every Catechiſm, and with <hi>much more</hi> in every little Syſtem: I mean, ſetting aſide his gaudy Flouriſhes and childiſh Exaggerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon mere <hi>Nothings;</hi> his Exclamations, and other Schemes of <hi>School-boys and Preachers Rhetoric,</hi> with which the World has been ſo long tired, as to nauſeate them. But this you will better ſee when we come to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of his Texts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To his own <hi>ridiculous</hi> Confidence of his Opinion, he adds as a farther Strength to it, ſome (impertinent) Quotations out of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> particularly from <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Thaumaturgus.</hi> He ſays farther at <hi>p.</hi> 61. that the Doctrine he has aſſerted in theſe Sermons is <hi>the Doctrine of the Primitive Church.</hi> And at <hi>p.</hi> 162. that <hi>Chriſtians have been in poſſeſſion of it above theſe ſixteen Centuries.</hi> I ſuſpected all along what an obſervant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Fathers and Church-Hiſtory Mr. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth</hi> is; but here he himſelf has ſhewed us, he conſiders not ſo much, as how many <hi>Years</hi> he is to reckon, from this preſent Year to our Saviour. Why, Man, the Socinians will give to thee and thy Fellow Tritheiſts the whole 16 Centuries which thou here inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt on, and are content with the <hi>ſeventeenth,</hi> of which (it ſhould ſeem) thou knoweſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The Century of our Saviour and the Apoſtles, <hi>the ſeventeenth</hi> from us, is to us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of all the reſt; and in the Opinion of all true Proteſtants that alone is worth more than all the reſt, if they were never ſo many Sixteens more. But we are ready to conteſt it in the Preſence of all the learned World, from the (genuine) Writings of the Fathers before the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, that the Doctrine of the preſent Church, of three <hi>equal, conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial</hi> and <hi>co-eternal</hi> Perſons, now called <hi>the Trinity,</hi> was expreſly rejected by them; that is to ſay, as conſubſtantial, co-eternal and co-equal, are now underſtood by the Church, and oppoſed by the Unitarians.</p>
               <p>Trinitarians boaſt in vain of the (pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Conſent of the antient Church with them, till they can anſwer the firſt Diſſertati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Quaternio</hi> of Diſſertati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, written by <hi>S. Curcellaeus</hi> againſt <hi>S. Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> concerning the Judgment of the Fathers and the Primitive Church, in the Queſtions of the Divinity of our Saviour, the Words <hi>Trinity, Conſubſtantial,</hi> &amp;c. Neither <hi>Mareſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> though an able and learned Perſon, nor any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205939:4"/> for him, have offered to reply; and the more learned of the Trinitarians, among the reſt D. <hi>Petavi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and the learned and exact Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> have owned the Diſſent of the <hi>ancient</hi> Church from the <hi>preſent,</hi> about the Senſe of the Words <hi>Conſubſtantial, Co-eternal,</hi> and <hi>Co-equal,</hi> in which the whole Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy concerning the Trinity doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From <hi>p.</hi> 55 to <hi>p.</hi> 61. he conſiders the Difficulties advanced by the Socinians (or Unitarians) on behalf of the Unity of God, and againſt the (imagined) Divinity of our Saviour; he <hi>learnedly</hi> diſtinguiſhes them into Heart-Difficulties, Wit-Difficulties, and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Difficulties: <hi>Heart-Difficulties</hi> being a new ſort of <hi>Cant,</hi> he explains by ſaying, <hi>p.</hi> 55, 56. that ſuch is the Temper the Heart of Man hath received from the Impreſſions of Sin, that whatſoever comes from Heaven is ſuſpected, though indeed there be no other Reaſon to ſuſpect it, but that it comes from Heaven. And again, Heaven ſaith it, this is ſufficient for Man to doubt, deny it, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict it.</p>
               <p>This is a <hi>Slander upon humane Nature;</hi> 'tis inconſiſtent with our rational Faculty or Power of Reaſoning; and the Experience of Mankind contradicts it. For every Body knows that the general Fault of the World is not <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> but <hi>Inconſideration,</hi> and an Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Neglect of Duty from a <hi>vain</hi> Hope and Expectance that we have yet time enough and to ſpare, in which to amend all Faults, and make our Peace with Heaven. But if Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> is indeed acquainted with any, who therefore will not believe, becauſe <hi>Heaven</hi> hath ſaid it, as he affirms; my Advice to him is, to let thoſe <hi>reſolute</hi> People alone, for if they will not believe <hi>Heaven,</hi> they will much leſs believe <hi>him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as to all theſe Difficulties (the Heart-difficulties, Wit-difficulties, and Scripture-difficulties) which he hath purſued in divers Pages, he hath repreſented them ſo <hi>meanly,</hi> as well as anſwered them ſo <hi>weakly,</hi> that the Socinians own them not for theirs. We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the Reader to inform himſelf of the <hi>Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or Arguments advanced by the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, not from Mr. <hi>Lamoth,</hi> but from our own Writings, that is to ſay, from the <hi>Brief Notes on the Creed of</hi> Athanaſius; the firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>the brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians; the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Reſolution concerning the Trinity and Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; the Trinitarian Scheme, with Notes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; the Anſwers to Dr.</hi> Sherlock, <hi>Dr.</hi> Wallis, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Milbourn. In which Pamphlets he will ſee enough to furniſh him out againſt a much abler Sophiſter than Monſieur <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His laſt General Argument againſt us is this, that we cannot endeavour the Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Opinions wichout troubling the Peace of Mens Conſciences, and ſetting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians together by the Ears. They own us, ſaith he, to be in a State of Salvation, and that we have retained <hi>all the Fundamental and ſaving Points of Chriſtianity;</hi> where therefore is <hi>the Charity</hi> of theſe <hi>raſh</hi> Perſons, to ſhake a Doctrine which cannot be attacked with any Succeſs, without filling the Conſciences of Men with <hi>Trouble,</hi> and ſhedding whole <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> of Chriſtian Blood? Such a Deſign as this cannot be the Effect of any thing but <hi>Pride:</hi> they have a Mind to diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the Novelty of their Opinions, and to advance their own Glory, by abating that of Jeſus Chriſt. This is the Sum of what he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 62, 63.</p>
               <p>He is the unhappieſt Man alive at arguing a Point, whether great or ſmall. Let us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to be as he ſays, that Trinitarians have retained <hi>all the Fundamental Points of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> muſt we not therefore open our Mouths in Defence of ſo ſacred a Truth as the Unity of God? The Papiſts have retained all the Fundamental Points of Chriſtianity, in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all Proteſtants but the Socinians; their Fault and Error is only this, that they have <hi>added</hi> abundance of <hi>Wood, Hay and Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> to the <hi>Gold, Silver and precious Stones:</hi> Shall I ſay hereupon with this Author, <hi>where therefore was the Charity of thoſe raſh Perſons,</hi> the Authors of the French Reformation, <hi>to fill the Conſciences of Men with Trouble, and hazard the ſhedding</hi> (nay actually to ſhed, as they did) <hi>whole Torrents of Chriſtian Blood?</hi> He ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 62.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205939:4"/> Nothing can warrant the Attempts of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians, if the Doctrine which Trinitarians teach and believe is <hi>conſiſtent with Salvation.</hi> Then ſay I, what ſhall excuſe the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> for Proteſtants believe Popery to be <hi>conſiſtent with Salvation?</hi> and I do not think that this bold Man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will ſay, all Papiſts are damned.</p>
               <p>But I deſire to know of him, why <hi>Torrents of Chriſtian Blood muſt be ſhed,</hi> on Occaſion of the Socinians <hi>peaceable</hi> Declaration of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which convince them of the Unity of God, and their modeſt Defence of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, from the Imputations of being <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators, Enemies of the Lord Jeſus, near Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to abſolute Irreligion;</hi> and ſuch like bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and inhumane Scandals? He doth not think the Socinians will ſhed <hi>his</hi> Blood, or any Man's elſe. He owns, <hi>p.</hi> 62. that we (at leaſt) ſeem to be <hi>innocent Lambs;</hi> nay our Principles and Carriage have wreſted alſo this from him: I am willing (ſaith he) to believe, that they cheriſh nothing of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Perſecution. What Danger then is there, that Torrents of Chriſtian Blood ſhould be ſhed? The Truth is, were it not for <hi>the Preachers,</hi> there never had any Blood been ſhed, by occaſion of the Queſtions and Diſputes about Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Matters had been fairly <hi>reaſoned,</hi> and we ſhould have thank'd one another for the Light and Information we received from one another, were it not that the <hi>Preachers</hi> by their importune Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours have always ſet one Part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Flock againſt the other: They have been nothing leſs, for the Generality of them, than their Office requires, even Preachers of mutual Candour, Charity, Forbearance, Love, ingenuous Freedom of Mind, againſt the unhappy Biaſſes of Education, Prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, Intereſt, and other Adverſaries, to the Diſcovery of Truth, whether Religious or Philoſophical.</p>
               <p>It can be <hi>nothing,</hi> he ſaith, but our Pride, and a Deſire to advance our own Glory by the Novelty of our Opinions, that occaſions our Diſſent from other Chriſtians. Nay ſo wicked are we, as well as vain, that to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt our ſelves we care not how we abuſe Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, whom we confeſs to be our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and Saviour: But Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> ſhould have been very ſure of it before he proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all People, that we honour our ſelves more than we honour Jeſus Chriſt, nay to the Diſhonour of Jeſus Chriſt; and that our Bottom is nothing but <hi>Pride.</hi> 'Tis <hi>nothing,</hi> it ſhould ſeem with him, that we have this Charge given to us in the very firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me;</hi> no other, whether they be <hi>real</hi> Perſons, or only <hi>imaginary</hi> and <hi>fictitious</hi> ones. 'Tis <hi>nothing</hi> that our Saviour ſays to the young Man whom he loved, <hi>Why calleſt thou me Good, there is none good ſave one, that is God.</hi> Nothing that St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells all Chriſtians; <hi>there is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> Nothing that an Almighty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, an Almighty Son, and an Almighty Spirit, different in Number from both, can no more be conceived to be one Almighty, than a mortal Father, a mortal Son, and a third Perſon who alſo is mortal, can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be but one Mortal, not three Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals. If you require <hi>Scripture,</hi> we bring the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of our Saviour, at <hi>John 17. 3. the Father</hi> (ſaith he there) <hi>is the only true God.</hi> If you demand <hi>Reaſon,</hi> we demonſtrate it with more than mathematical Certainty, that three <hi>Divine</hi> Perſons muſt needs be three Gods, becauſe <hi>three Divine Perſons</hi> is nothing elſe but the Periphraſis or Circumlocution for <hi>three Gods,</hi> even as three <hi>humane Perſons</hi> and three <hi>angelical Perſons</hi> are the Circumlocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Periphraſes for three <hi>Men</hi> and three <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi>'s Anſwer is, that all this (and an hundred times more) is <hi>nothing.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, that the Sun cannot ſhine ſo brightly as to force it ſelf to be ſeen; for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, 'tis but ſhutting ones Eyes, and the Sun ſhines in vain.</p>
               <p>He urges us with it, that we grant that Trinitarians have retained <hi>all the Fundamental Articles of Religion.</hi> Who grants it? Firſt, they themſelves own, that if they are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they are <hi>Idolaters;</hi> they are conſcious, nay they profeſs and diſpute for it, that they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205939:5"/> are guilty of Polytheiſm, if there be no ſuch Perſons as they have imagined, even an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Son of God, and an Almighty and Living Spirit, different in Number from that Son, and from God the Father of all.</p>
               <p>But the Socinians grant it: I cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for every particular Writer of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians; for my own part, I ſhall never grant that the Unity of God, or but one <hi>Divine</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is not a Fundamental Article. My Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is this; 'tis confeſſed on all ſides, that both the Covenants (the Old as well as the New) is between the one true God, on the one part, and his Servant <hi>Man</hi> on the other: but if ſo, the Covenant is utterly diſſolved on our Part, if beſides this one true God with whom we are in Covenant, we ſet up, and equal alſo with him, another Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether <hi>real</hi> or <hi>imaginary</hi> ones: I mean ſuch as knowingly do ſo, and worſhip ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. As the Covenant of Allegiance and Protection (Allegiance on the Part of the People, and Protection on the Part of the King) is broken on the Peoples Part, if they ſet up or own any other Perſon as King, beſides him who of Right is ſo. But come we now to the true Strength of his Book, the Texts that he hath alledged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On his first Propoſition from the Words of his Text.</head>
               <p>HE chooſeth for his Subject or Text the Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 6. 7. <hi>Who being in the Form of God, thought it not Robbery to be equal with God, but made himſelf of no Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and took upon him the Form of a Servant, and was made in the Likeneſs of Men.</hi> He ſaith theſe Words preſent us with three Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That Jeſus Chriſt <hi>was</hi> before he was in the Form of Man.</item>
                  <item>2. That he was <hi>in the Form of God</hi> before he was in the Form of Man.</item>
                  <item>3. That he thought it not Robbery to be equal with his heavenly Father.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt of theſe, that Jeſus <hi>was</hi> before he was in the Form of Man, he proveth thus: The Text ſays, that <hi>being in the Form of God, he humbled himſelf;</hi> or as 'tis in the Original, <hi>he emptied himſelf.</hi> But <hi>what Senſe</hi> ſhall we make of the Words, ſaith he, if it be not true, that our Saviour before his Birth of the Bleſſed Virgin, was in a more glorious State than was that State upon which he entred at his Nativity?</p>
               <p>'Tis an Impiety that runs through our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's whole Book, that the Scriptures have not ſpoken Senſe, if they do not always mean as he would have them. I pray, Sir, ſee the ſeventh Chapter of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn,</hi> and then tell me, whether the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians have not made Senſe of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, without ſuppoſing (as Trinitarians here do) that <hi>Paul</hi> advanceth <hi>another,</hi> or a <hi>ſecond</hi> God! It is ſhown there, that to be <hi>in the Form of God,</hi> is common to our Saviour with all other Men: all Men (ſay the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) are made in the Similitude, Form or Likeneſs of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 9. But our Bleſſed Saviour was more in the Form or Likeneſs of God than any other Man or Men, becauſe he had a more perfect Holineſs, and a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Power and Authority over the Devils, Diſeaſes, the Sea, the Winds, for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of that Doctrine which he was to deliver to Men in the Name of God.</p>
               <p>Our Engliſh Tranſlation adds, <hi>he thought it not Robbery to be equal with God.</hi> But 'tis now known even to School-boys, that the Greek Words ſhould have been rendred to a juſt contrary Purpoſe: their Lexicon upon the Greek Teſtament (made by the induſtrious and learned <hi>G. Paſor</hi>) teaches them to read here, <hi>Non rapuit aequalitatem cum Deo;</hi> he aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not to himſelf to be equal with God. So that the Senſe is, though the Lord Chriſt was in a greater Likeneſs to God than ever any other Creature was, yet he was far from imitating the Pride and Ambition of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> he took not on him to be equal with God; but on the contrary, he took on him the Form of a Servant, that is, to ſet us an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Humility and mutual Toleration, he ſubmitted to Reproach, and even to Blows,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205939:5"/> without reviling again, or other ways aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging himſelf on thoſe that wronged him.</p>
               <p>Every one knows what Great <hi>Eraſmus</hi> hath ſaid upon this Text, that though the Fathers were wont to urge it againſt the <hi>Arians,</hi> to prove that the Son is <hi>God equal with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> yet the Apoſtle, ſaith he, had no ſuch Intention. Therefore he approveth the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of St. <hi>Ambroſe, Non defendit ſibi aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem;</hi> Chriſt did not defend himſelf to be equal with God. <hi>M. Luther,</hi> the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former (<hi>lib. de duplici juſt.</hi>) admoniſhes his Reader, that we muſt not underſtand this Text <hi>affirmatively,</hi> but <hi>negatively;</hi> not as ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt made himſelf equal with God, but as denying that he is equal with God; which I mention only that the leſs learned Reader may know, that beſides the Socinians, ſome of the principal Interpreters and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, among our Oppoſers themſelves, have been aware, that this is not a Context to be inſiſted on, as a Proof of our Saviour's Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Our Tranſlation goes on; and <hi>took on him the Form of a Servant, and was made in the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men.</hi> I could never yet ſee any Greek Teſtament that ſo reads the Words; and I dare affirm that no Greek Copy, whether Printed or Manuſcript, ſo reads. All the Original Copies (with one Conſent) read thus; <hi>But made himſelf of no Reputation, taking the Form of a Servant: being made in the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men, and found in faſhion as a Man,</hi> (that is, being a Man like to all other Men; ſo the Trinitarian Interpreters themſelves under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Words) <hi>he humbled himſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obedient to Death, even the Death of the Croſs;</hi> i. e. he ſubmitted to the unjuſt Powers that then were, and chearfully underwent Death, even the painful and ignominious Death of the Croſs. This, all learned Men know and own, is the true Reading of this Text; and it blows away at once all the little Devices that Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi> uſes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert its plain and obvious meaning.</p>
               <p>But in purſuance of this firſt Propoſition from his Text, that Chriſt <hi>was</hi> before he <hi>was made Man,</hi> he urges divers other Texts, <hi>nine</hi> in all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſaith, that Jeſus Chriſt declares, that he <hi>was come down from Heaven, and that he was in Heaven, before ever he aſcended thither.</hi> We anſwer, Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> makes uſe of a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Bible of his own; he will never be able to ſhow us ſuch a Text in any Bible but that which is in his private Cuſtody.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt ſaith, <hi>John 1. 30. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me cometh a Man who is preferred before me, for he was before me.</hi> We anſwer with his learned Country-man <hi>Th. Beza,</hi> the Lord Chriſt was preferred before <hi>John,</hi> becauſe though he was after <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Time,</hi> yet he <hi>was before him in Merit and Dignity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 9. Neither let us tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them</hi> (the Iſraelites in the Wilderneſs) <hi>tempted, and were deſtroyed of Serpents.</hi> This Text were indeed to the Purpoſe of our Saviour's Pre-exiſtence, if it had been ſaid here, that the Iſraelites in the Wilderneſs <hi>tempted (i. e.</hi> murmured againſt) <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But this is not ſaid; and 'tis certain they tempted <hi>God,</hi> not the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Heb. 11. 26. <hi>He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Reproach of Chriſt before the Treaſures of Egypt.</hi> We anſwer, with almoſt all the Commentators on the Scriptures; the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were reproached by their Oppreſſors the Egyptians, with their Hopes of a Saviour, or Meſſias, or Chriſt; but <hi>Moſes</hi> preferred this <hi>Reproach,</hi> as the Egyptians counted it, before all the Treaſures of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Our Saviour again ſaith, <hi>John 8. 58. Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was I am.</hi> It is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as when 'tis ſaid of the ſame our Lord Chriſt, <hi>Rev. 13. 8. The Lamb who was ſlain from the Beginning of the World.</hi> Chriſt <hi>was,</hi> and <hi>was ſlain</hi> before <hi>Abraham,</hi> and before the Foundation of the World, not actually, but <hi>in the Ordination and Decree of God.</hi> Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of him, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 20. Who verily was fore-ordained</hi> (not only before <hi>Abraham,</hi> but) <hi>before the Foundation of the World, but was manifeſt in theſe laſt Days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. We are aſſured by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 19. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt preached to the Spirits that were diſobedient in the Time of</hi> Noah. Here again he maketh uſe of his own private Bible; when
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205939:6"/> he puts the Text in the Words of the known and authentick Bibles, we will give him an Account of it. In the mean time he may ſee it explained, and the Explication warranted by the Authority of thirty Fathers, in the fourth Letter of the <hi>Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. 'Tis affirmed by the Evangeliſt <hi>John,</hi> ch. 1. 1. <hi>In the Beginning was the WORD.</hi> We anſwer, In the Beginning <hi>of the Goſpel-State Chriſt was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The ſame Evangeliſt ſaith, <hi>John 1. 3. All things were made by him</hi> (by the WORD) <hi>and without him was not any thing made, that was made.</hi> We grant it, in that Senſe in which only 'tis conſiſtent and reconcilable with thoſe innumerable Texts which aſſure us, that only God was the Maker of the firſt or <hi>old Creation.</hi> But St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks here of the new Creation, or the Goſpel-Oeconomy and State, <hi>that new Heavens and new Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs.</hi> This Creation was begun by the Miniſtry, and perfected by the Directions of the Lord Chriſt; who hath <hi>made all things new,</hi> by aboliſhing Judaiſm and Paganiſm, Ceremony and Idolatry, and introducing in their room moral Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Knowledg of the one true God. All theſe (great) things <hi>were made by him,</hi> (or as the Original may be rendred, <hi>done by him) and without him was nothing done that was done.</hi> But of this I have ſpoken fully, and I hope ſatisfactorily and effectually, with reſpect to conſidering Men, at <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. He finds too the Pre-eternity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, even in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who introduceth <hi>Wiſdom</hi> as ſaying, <hi>When there were no Depths,—before the Mountains were ſettled, before the Hills was I brought forth,</hi> Prov. 8. 24, 25. It falls out here ſomewhat unluckily, for our Author, and ſuch learned and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Interpreters as he is, that if this <hi>Wiſdom</hi> muſt needs be (not a <hi>Quality</hi> or Property, but) a real and a divine <hi>Perſon,</hi> ſhe was a <hi>Goddeſs,</hi> not a God. For 'tis undeniable that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of her as a <hi>Female:</hi> She begins her Diſcourſe at the firſt Verſe of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; <hi>Doth not Wiſdom cry, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding lift up HER Voice? SHE ſtandeth at the Top of the High Places;—SHE crieth at the Gates.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>On his ſecond and third Propoſitions.</head>
               <p>HIS ſecond Propoſition from his Text is, our Saviour <hi>was in the Form of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was in the Form of a Servant:</hi> which he taketh to be the ſame with this; he was in the Form of God <hi>before he was Man.</hi> He giveth two Reaſons:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe 'tis ſaid here, <hi>being in the Form of God, he emptied himſelf:</hi> So he tranſlates the Words inſtead of the Vulgar Engliſh, <hi>He made himſelf of no Reputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe otherways, the Oppoſition here plainly intended by the Apoſtle, will not be exact: for if <hi>the Form of God</hi> muſt be taken <hi>figuratively,</hi> ſo as only to make this Senſe, <hi>he was like unto God,</hi> was the Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or Likeneſs of God, as all other Men are; it will not anſwer to the other Member of the Oppoſition, which is not <hi>Figure</hi> but Reality; for <hi>the Form of a Servant,</hi> and <hi>the Likeneſs of Men,</hi> was intended to ſignify that Chriſt was a <hi>real</hi> Man, and not only that he was <hi>like to Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis a very thin Sophiſtry this: When our Author left off to ſpeak to the Vulgar, and would needs undertake (in this Paſſage) to ſpeak to the Learned, he ſhould have brought ſomething that was more ſubſtantial, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to blind ſuch Eyes as theirs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> he ſaith, Jeſus Chriſt was in the Form of God; that is, he was <hi>really God</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Man; becauſe this Text adds, that <hi>he emptied himſelf.</hi> Methinks that very Tranſlation which our Author has affected, ſhould have minded him of the Abſurdity and abſolute Impoſſibility of his Doctrine; for can he that is true God <hi>empty himſelf?</hi> can he leſſen, much leſs <hi>evacuate</hi> himſelf? To what Labyrinths, to what Mazes and Wilderneſſes does Error lead Men: God, they are forced to ſay, <hi>emptied</hi> himſelf; their next News
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205939:6"/> will be, <hi>he ceaſed to be,</hi> or was <hi>annihilated.</hi> But God is not only <hi>neceſſarily exiſtent,</hi> as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſpeak, but he is always <hi>neceſſarily the ſame;</hi> no Change, much leſs any <hi>emptying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> (as they have learned to <hi>cant</hi>) can befal to him.</p>
               <p>And why is this Preacher ſo hard to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that our Lord Chriſt might indeed (as he calls it) empty himſelf, though he were not God? Why cannot he call it an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying himſelf, that our Saviour ſubmitted to Apprehenſion, Perſecution, Scourging and Death, at that very time when he could, by his miraculous Power, have deſtroyed all his Enemies, both Jews and Romans? Why muſt we ſay Chriſt was <hi>in the Form of God,</hi> and interpret it thus, that <hi>he was God before he was Man,</hi> on the Account that he <hi>emptied</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; when the very contrary is ſo obvious and eaſy to be diſcerned, even this, that <hi>he was not God, becauſe he could and did empty himſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly;</hi> But the Oppoſition intended by the Apoſtle, he ſaith, will not be exact, if <hi>the Form of God</hi> muſt not ſignify <hi>Reality,</hi> as well as <hi>the Form of a Servant.</hi> Who told our Author, that <hi>the Form of a Servant</hi> here muſt be taken <hi>in Reality?</hi> Was our Saviour really a Servant to any Perſon? Do not all Men know, that he was only in the Form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, by his voluntary bearing of Injuries and Blows, without anſwering again, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging himſelf; that he might teach us by his Example, as well as by his Doctrine, to forgive one another? The Oppoſition is moſt exact: for as he was in the Form of God, without being really God; ſo he was in the Form of a Servant, without really being Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to any. But Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> would clap to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether theſe two, was <hi>in the Form of a Servant,</hi> and was <hi>in the Likeneſs of Men;</hi> as if they were one, or ſignified the ſame thing: and it is upon this Miſtake that his Argument pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds; But <hi>the Form of a Servant,</hi> and <hi>the Likeneſs of Men,</hi> are moſt different things: and he ought alſo to have been aware, that <hi>a new</hi> Senſe begins at theſe Words, <hi>Being made in the Likeneſs of Men,</hi> as I have ſhown before.</p>
               <p>His laſt Propoſition, from his Text, is, that Jeſus Chriſt did not think it Robbery to be equal with God; ſo he words his Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>p.</hi> 9. I have obſerved before, that now the very <hi>Boys</hi> know, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is not to be rendred, <hi>he thought it not Robbery to be equal with God;</hi> but <hi>non rapuit aequalitatem cum Deo,</hi> he aſſumed not to himſelf to be equal with God. If Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi> knew of this Tranſlation, but <hi>diſſembled it,</hi> he prevaricated with his Hearers, and ſought <hi>diſingenuouſly</hi> to impoſe upon them: if he knew of it, but <hi>diſliked it,</hi> why did he not give his Reaſons againſt it?</p>
               <p>Here our Author takes leave of his Text, and falls to proving our Saviour's Divinity from the <hi>5th</hi> Chapter of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel: the Words he picketh out are theſe; <hi>As the Father raiſeth up the Dead, and quickneth them, even ſo the Son quickneth whom he will.—That all Men ſhould honour the Son, even as they honour the Father.—The Hour is coming, and now is, when the Dead ſhall hear the Voice of the Son of God; and they that hear ſhall live. For as the Father hath Life in himſelf, ſo hath he given to the Son, to have Life in himſelf.</hi> And as if theſe Words had ended the whole Controverſy between him and the Socinians, he falls to his French <hi>Rhodomontades,</hi> and <hi>Paedagogical</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs. He tells us, <q>'Tis impoſſible for any to equal himſelf more poſitively with God than our Saviour here doth in theſe Words: They do not in the leaſt need a Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to warrant us, to ſay with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that our Saviour thought it not Robbery to be equal with God his Father.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He takes no notice, that in what Senſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we are to underſtand it, that <hi>the Son quickneth whom he will,</hi> and is to be <hi>honoured as the Father,</hi> and <hi>will make the Dead to hear his Voice,</hi> and <hi>hath Life in himſelf:</hi> yet he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth here, that <hi>the Father hath given them to him:</hi> that is, he profeſſeth that himſelf is not God, becauſe he hath not theſe Powers of himſelf, but <hi>by the Goodneſs and Gift of another Perſon.</hi> Our Author too paſſes it over, that as a farther Caution againſt being miſtaken by any, our Saviour ſolemnly <hi>prefaces</hi> his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205939:7"/> whole Diſcourſe here with theſe Words, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, verily I ſay to you, the Son can do nothing of himſelf,</hi> nothing by his own <hi>proper</hi> Power and Authority; and that he <hi>concludeth</hi> them with another Antidote, againſt being either miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood or miſrepreſented, even with this, <hi>the Works which the Father hath given me</hi> (hath given me Command and Power) <hi>to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, bear witneſs of me, that the Father hath ſent me, i. e.</hi> that I am the Father's Meſſenger and Ambaſſador. Finally, he omitteth too, that all theſe Expreſſions are ſo interpreted by the more Learned even of his own Party, as that they ſuppoſe that our Lord Chriſt here ſpeaks of himſelf only as a <hi>Man:</hi> for they ſay, <hi>the Son quickneth whom he will,</hi> in that he raiſed from the dead <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the Widow's Son, and ſome others, and could have raiſed many more, even as many as he ſhould pleaſe. And <hi>all Men ſhould honour the Son as they honour the Father;</hi> becauſe the Ambaſſador repreſenting the Majeſty of him that ſends him, his Perſon is <hi>ſacroſanct,</hi> and in divers Reſpects to be honoured as his <hi>Principal</hi> is, by the Law of Nations. Again, <hi>the Dead ſhall hear the Voice of the Son of God;</hi> for he would call divers from the Dead, as former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had done. 'Tis added, laſt of all, <hi>he hath Life in himſelf:</hi> all agree, that the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, he ſo poſſeſſeth the Fountain of Life, by the Gift of God, as that he reſtoreth Life to whomſoever he will. If Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> was not aware of theſe Interpretations, 'tis his <hi>Dulneſs</hi> or his <hi>Negligence;</hi> if he was, that he diſſembles them, is his <hi>Diſhoneſty;</hi> out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Coat I am deſirous to think the former.</p>
               <p>I ſee nothing further that is conſiderable in his firſt Diſcourſe, but an impious Reflection on the Perſon of our Saviour, and another on the Scriptures. Of our Saviour he ſaith at <hi>p.</hi> 19. that if he is not God, the Sum of the Chriſtian Religion will be this, that a certain Teacher is come to inſtruct Men by exact Morality, and by a perfect Example, with regard to thoſe Vertues that we ought to practiſe in our Lives; <hi>but against whom are ſome things to be objected, with regard to thoſe Vertues that are of uſe at the Point of Death.</hi> This uſual Scandal of ſome Trinitarians up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Saviour, that he was <hi>puſillanimous</hi> or fearful at the Point of Death, is fully anſwered at <hi>Chap. 11. pag.</hi> 55. of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn.</hi> But I wonder that they ſhould not conſider that this (falſe) Charge of theirs againſt our common Maſter is much more colourable on their Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, and much leſs excuſable than on ours: For <hi>we</hi> ſay, the Lord Chriſt was a Prophet; <hi>they</hi> ſay, he was alſo God. Now that a <hi>Man</hi> ſhould have quick Apprehenſions of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Death, eſpecially of a Death <hi>ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, painful</hi> and <hi>undeſerved,</hi> is no wonder, be ſure is not ſinful; but that a <hi>God-man,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> think him, ſhould be diſturbed at Death, is altogether unaccountable.</p>
               <p>As to the Scriptures, he ſays at <hi>p.</hi> 20. If Jeſus Chriſt was no more than a <hi>Man,</hi> thoſe Texts of Scripture that ſpeak of that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mercy and Love of God, in giving this Saviour to Mankind, <hi>have no Senſe at all.</hi> He affirms moreover, that for God to make only a <hi>Creature,</hi> that by his Means he might ſave ſo many <hi>Millions</hi> of Men, <hi>was no more than if he had given a Straw to ſave them.</hi> I had thought (I confeſs) that French Miniſters would n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have <hi>licenſed</hi> ſuch <hi>Outrages</hi> to the Preſs: And if it was with ſo little Regard to the Honour of our Saviour, and to the Holy Scriptures, that they managed their Controverſies in <hi>France,</hi> I had almoſt ſaid they were deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baniſh'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To his Objections concerning the Names of God, which he ſaith are alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Lord Christ in Holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Lamoth</hi>'s ſecond Diſcourſe begins with an Acknowledgment, that <hi>to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake a Man for God is the moſt dangerous of all Errors whatſoever.</hi> Is it ſo, then why has he ſaid ſo often, that nothing can excuſe the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians for oppoſing the Doctrine of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Divinity? For if that Doctrine is an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205939:7"/> Error, he himſelf has confeſs'd, <hi>'tis the moſt dangerous of all Errors whatſoever.</hi> But he ſaith, that Doctrine is no Error; for that our Saviour is true God, is made evident by theſe three Obſervations.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. He hath <hi>the Names</hi> of God given to him by the Writers of Holy Scripture.</item>
                  <item>2. Beſides the Names of God he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>the Attributes</hi> of God aſcribed to him.</item>
                  <item>3. And to put the whole Matter out of doubt, <hi>the Worſhip</hi> due only to God is alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Scripture, and there <hi>required to be given</hi> to him.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> The Lord Chriſt hath <hi>the Names</hi> of God given to him, <hi>John 1. 1. The WORD was God.</hi> Nay he is called the <hi>true</hi> God, and the <hi>great</hi> God, 1 <hi>John 5. 20. Titus</hi> 2. 3. He ſaith moreover, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Titus,</hi> called our Saviour <hi>God, at least four or five times;</hi> and after a Line or two forgetting himſelf, he ſaith in that ſhort Epiſtle, Chriſt is called God <hi>three or four times.</hi> Finally, he citeth ſome Texts in which he thinketh the Name <hi>Jehovah</hi> is beſtowed on our Lord Chriſt: But becauſe we are ſure he cannot ſhew us that Jeſus Chriſt is once called God in the Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> but only out of that ſingle Bible which is in his own keeping; and becauſe the Words of St. <hi>John, the true God,</hi> and of St. <hi>Paul, the great God,</hi> are evidently ſpoken not of our Saviour, but of God; and becauſe what he ſaith of the Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> that 'tis applied to our Saviour Chriſt, is abundantly anſwered at <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn;</hi> therefore here I ſhall only conſider what he hath offered on the other Texts, in which (as 'tis commonly ſuppoſed) our Saviour hath the Name <hi>God</hi> given to him.</p>
               <p>He takes notice, that <hi>we</hi> anſwer, that our Saviour is called <hi>God</hi> ſometimes, becauſe <hi>he repreſented the Perſon of God, bringing to us the Commands of God;</hi> for which Reaſon <hi>Moſes</hi> is called God, and that by God himſelf; <hi>Exod. 7. 1. See I have made thee a God to</hi> Pharaoh. <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo is in this Reſpect called <hi>God, Pſal.</hi> 45. 6, and 11. and ſo are the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Princes and Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 6. but by our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 10. 34, 35. Nay it appears by 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 11, 13, 14. that the Prophets who ſpoke in the Name and Perſon of God, were therefore called <hi>Elohim,</hi> Gods. To the Examples of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> ſaith nothing, I ſuppoſe, becauſe he ſaw that neither of his two Shifts would ſerve him at all againſt thoſe evident Inſtances: But to that of <hi>Moſes</hi> he ſaith, his being <hi>a God</hi> is limited to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> 'tis ſaid of him by God, <hi>I have made thee a God to</hi> Pharaoh, not to others. But our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is called God <hi>abſolutely,</hi> without any Limitation to this or that Perſon or Perſons. To the Example of the Princes and Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he ſaith, 'tis not any Magiſtrate <hi>in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,</hi> who is ever called God, but all of them in <hi>general;</hi> but our Saviour is <hi>in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> called God.</p>
               <p>Let us begin with his ſecond Anſwer, that no Prince or Magiſtrate <hi>in particular</hi> is called <hi>God;</hi> but it is ſaid of them <hi>in general</hi> only, <hi>Ye are Gods.</hi> But why has Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> parted with ſuch a Secret, that <hi>he underſtands not Grammar, no nor common Senſe?</hi> For does not every <hi>ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Man know, that <hi>Generals</hi> include in them <hi>Particulars?</hi> If I ſay to <hi>many, Ye are Gods,</hi> do I not thereby ſay to every one of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Thou art a God?</hi> When the King ſaith to his Houſe of Peers, <hi>My Lords;</hi> or to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Houſe, <hi>Gentlemen;</hi> doth he not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg every one of the former to be <hi>a Lord,</hi> and every one of the other to be <hi>a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man?</hi> And why hath our Author ſo unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly ſaid, that no Magiſtrate, Prince or Angel, is ever <hi>in particular</hi> called God or <hi>a God</hi> in Holy Scripture? <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> are ſo called <hi>in particular,</hi> Pſal. 45. 6, 11. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 11, 13, 14. The Angel that ſpoke to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the burning Buſh, is called God; and ſo is <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, <hi>Exod. 3. 2, 4. Exod.</hi> 7. 1. Other <hi>particular</hi> Angels are called Gods (it may be) twenty times in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by Confeſſion of the ableſt Criticks and Interpreters of our Author's own Party.</p>
               <p>Nor is his firſt Anſwer a-whit better than the ſecond, but rather leſs conſiderate and adviſed: He ſaith, <hi>Moſes</hi> is not called God <hi>ſimply</hi> and <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but <hi>with Limitation;</hi> he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205939:8"/> is ſaid to be a God <hi>to a particular Perſon,</hi> a God to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> not abſolutely God or <hi>a</hi> God. Now either he will <hi>abide</hi> by this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as ſound and good, or he will not. If he will not, then our Anſwer (that <hi>Moſes</hi> as well as Chriſt is called <hi>God</hi>) remains in its full Force. But if he ſaith, he will <hi>abide</hi> by it as a good and ſufficient Reply to us, then he hath given up to us that only Text, in which the Name <hi>God</hi> is beſtowed on our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: For the Socinians eaſily ſatisfy the more learned of their Oppoſers, that all the other Texts in which 'tis by ſome ſuppoſed that our Lord Chriſt is called <hi>God,</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed intended, not of the Lord Chriſt, but of the Almighty <hi>Father,</hi> whom all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg to be God: but the Words of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> (at <hi>John</hi> 20. 28.) Thomas <hi>ſaid to him</hi> (to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) <hi>my Lord and my God,</hi> are generally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, as well by Socinians as others, to be ſpoken <hi>to</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the Lord Chriſt. To this Text therefore <hi>Socinus</hi> anſwers, in the ſame manner that Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> doth here concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Moſes,</hi> that the Lord Chriſt is not called God, <hi>ſimply</hi> and <hi>abſolutely;</hi> but <hi>with Limitation</hi> to a particular Perſon, he was a God to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas: Thomas</hi> doth not ſay <hi>abſolutely,</hi> O Lord God, but <hi>my</hi> Lord and <hi>my</hi> God; the perſonal Pronoun <hi>my</hi> limits the Senſe of the Words to <hi>Thomas,</hi> and ſuffers us not to extend them, or take them in an abſolute or a general Senſe. For my part, I always thought this to be a <hi>frivolous</hi> ſhift, but it ſhould ſeem Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> approves of it; he thinks a Perſon is not really called a God, or hath not the Name <hi>God</hi> really given to him, if he is not called God <hi>abſolutely, without Limitation</hi> to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſon. I ſay therefore, let him take his Choice; either let him ſay, he will not <hi>abide</hi> by this Anſwer; and then <hi>our</hi> Anſwer alſo (that <hi>Moſes</hi> too is called <hi>God</hi>) will be ſufficient and home; or let him abide by it, and then he has given up to us that only Text in which the Name <hi>God</hi> is given to the Lord Chriſt, even theſe Words of <hi>Thomas, My Lord and my God.</hi> But I deſire you, Sir, to remember alſo, how clearly I have ſatisfied that Text, the Words of <hi>Thomas,</hi> at <hi>Chap. 6. p.</hi> 32, 33. of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To his Proofs that <hi>the Attributes</hi> of God are aſcribed to Christ.</head>
               <p>HIS ſecond Proof, or rather his ſecond <hi>Claſs</hi> of Proofs, that the Lord Chriſt is God, is this, that <hi>the Attributes</hi> of the Divine Nature are aſcribed to him no leſs than to God. And I will make choice, ſaith he, of <hi>ſix</hi> of the Divine Attributes to verify my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; Eternity, Immenſity, Holineſs, Knowledg, Power and Mercy. Theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, ſaith he, are in the Lord Chriſt, <hi>in ſuch manner as belongs to God only;</hi> therefore the Lord Chriſt is alſo God.</p>
               <p>Firſt; For Eternity, he ſaith, 'tis proved to be in Chriſt, becauſe the Author to the <hi>Hebrews (Ch.</hi> 1. 11.) applies to our Lord Chriſt what had been ſaid by the Pſalmiſt concerning God, namely theſe Words of Pſal. 102. 26, 27. <hi>They</hi> (the Heavens) <hi>ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt endure; yea, all of them ſhall wax old like a Garment: as a Veſture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed; but thou art the ſame, and thy Years have no end.</hi> He quoteth this Text to prove <hi>the Eternity</hi> of our Lord Chriſt; that I may uſe his own Words, <hi>not only the Eternity which is to come, but his Pre-eternity, or the Eternity which is paſt.</hi> If he had alledged it to prove the fifth Attribute, <hi>the Power</hi> of the Lord Chriſt, becauſe 'tis here ſaid, <hi>he ſhall change the Heavens:</hi> We would have informed him, that the Heavens here ſpoken of, are not the <hi>material</hi> Heavens, but <hi>the new Heavens and new Earth,</hi> or the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Oeconomy and State of things, as I have largely proved at <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn.</hi> But ſeeing he citeth this Text to prove the Pre-eternity of our Saviour, or the <hi>Eternity which is paſt,</hi> we are conſtrained to anſwer in ſhort, that (till he ſhows it more particularly) we cannot diſcern the leaſt Shadow of a Pretence to draw that Concluſion from this Text.</p>
               <p>But the ſame Epiſtle to the Hebrews ſaith, <hi>This Man</hi> (Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>was counted worthy of more Glory than</hi> Moſes; <hi>inaſmuch as he who hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205939:8"/> built the Houſe hath more Honour than the Houſe, Heb.</hi> 3. 3. We anſwer, the Houſe here meant is <hi>Domus Dei,</hi> the Chriſtian Church, of which the Lord Chriſt was (under God) the Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but this Houſe was not from Eternity.</p>
               <p>Next he quoteth <hi>Heb. 7. 3. He was without Father and without Mother, without Deſcent; having neither Beginning of Days, nor end of Life.</hi> But all Interpreters, of both Perſwaſions, are agreed, that theſe Words are ſpoken of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec,</hi> whoſe Father and Mother, and the time of his Birth and Death, not being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded any where in Scripture; he is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>figuratively</hi> ſaid to be without Father and Mother, without Beginning or End of Life. But he is not herein like to the Son of God, (the Time of whoſe Birth and Death is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in Scripture, and whoſe <hi>Mother</hi> was Bleſſed <hi>Mary,</hi> his <hi>Father</hi> the everlaſting God) but he is like the Son of God, in that <hi>he abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a Prieſt for ever:</hi> Which he is ſaid to do in reſpect of the Continuance (not of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but) of his <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> which ceaſeth not, as did the <hi>Levitical,</hi> but is continued for ever in the Prieſthood of the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14. 'tis ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt through the eternal Spirit offered himſelf to God.</hi> This <hi>eternal</hi> Spirit Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> thinks was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's own eternal Spirit; but he hath not quoted the Place right: the Words are theſe, <hi>Who, through the eternal Spirit, offered himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Spot to God;</hi> i. e. the Lord Chriſt by the Co-operation of the Spirit and Grace of God, was ſinleſs and ſpotleſs, and ſo offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as an <hi>immaculate</hi> Sacrifice to God. The Emphaſis lyeth not, in <hi>offering himſelf,</hi> or <hi>by the Spirit,</hi> but in offering himſelf <hi>without Spot,</hi> which was by the Co-operation of God's Grace or Spirit.</p>
               <p>I ſee not what Weight or Force there is in his next Allegation, <hi>Heb. 13. 8. Jeſus the ſame Yeſterday, to Day, and for ever.</hi> When he tells us what he means by it, or how he forms an Argument from it, we will conſider of it. But whereas he adds, that the Words at <hi>Rev. 1. 8. I am Alpha and Omega, the Beginning and the Ending, ſaith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which ſhall be, the Almighty,</hi> are ſpoken of the Lord Chriſt; he ſhould have proved it as well as ſaid it, which when he does, we will give him the Cauſe: But he may ſee in the fourth Letter of the <hi>Brief Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> a demonſtrative Proof, that the Words are ſpoken of God, not of the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Come we now to the Attribute of Immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, by which, he ſaith, our Saviour is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in all Places at the ſame time. For <hi>this</hi> he bringeth firſt thoſe Words of our Saviour, <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my Name, I am in the midst of them,</hi> Matth. 18. 20. We anſwer, Chriſt, though in Heaven, is in the midſt of his People, <hi>partly</hi> by prophetick <hi>Viſion</hi> and Knowledg, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Coloſſians, <hi>Though I be abſent in the Fleſh, I am preſent in the Spirit, joying and beholding your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> Col. 2. 5. And <hi>partly</hi> by that powerful Aid and Help which he affordeth to us; what by his Mediation with God for all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. what by the Intervention of Angels, who are under his Directions, and by him engaged in the Defence of the Faithful, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14.</p>
               <p>As another Proof of our Saviour's Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence, he gives us <hi>John 3. 13. No Man hath aſcended into Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven, even the Son of Man, which is in Heaven.</hi> If he will needs have the laſt Words to be, <hi>which IS in Heaven,</hi> contrary to all the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Criticks, who read here, <hi>which WAS in Heaven:</hi> We ſay, the Lord Chriſt was then in Heaven, was in Heaven while he was upon Earth; in the ſame Senſe that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith the like of himſelf, when he propoundeth himſelf for an Example to the Philippians, Phil. 3. 20. <hi>Our Converſation is in Heaven:</hi> Namely, by Heavenly-mindedneſs, an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Frame of Spirit, by heavenly Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Contemplations. Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes the Conſideration of theſe two Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, Eternity and Immenſity, with this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, that <hi>they are abſolutely incommunicable to Creatures.</hi> But the moſt eminent Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have been of Opinion, that they are both of them found in <hi>Matter</hi> or <hi>Bodies,</hi> as they ſpeak. They ſuppoſe, that the <hi>Moles,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:205939:9"/> Matter or Subſtance of which the World is made, was <hi>from all Eternity;</hi> and that 'tis <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe</hi> and <hi>interminable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Attribute is <hi>Holineſs;</hi> and the Lord Chriſt, ſaith our Author, <hi>is holy, as God is holy.</hi> He proveth this, becauſe the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> heard the Seraphims make this Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to God, <hi>Holy, holy, holy is the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> And the Evangeliſt St. <hi>John</hi> aſſures us, that this Lord of Hoſts whom the Seraphims praiſed, was our Lord Chriſt; <hi>John 12. 41. Theſe things ſaid</hi> Iſaias, <hi>when he ſaw his Glory, and ſpake of him.</hi> But the Criticks (both Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Moderns) of our Author's own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, plainly ſaw, that the Words of St. <hi>John</hi> are intended, not of the Lord Chriſt, but of God. They give two Reaſons, which Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> (in his next) may do well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move. They obſerve, that the Words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately foregoing are certainly ſpoken of God; and that the beſt Greek Copies read here expreſly, <hi>theſe things ſaid</hi> Iſaias, <hi>when he ſaw GOD's Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He goes on; We ſay further, <hi>the Lord Christ knows whatſoever God knows.</hi> He thinks this <hi>wild</hi> Affirmation is proved by St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Words to our Saviour, <hi>Thou knoweſt all things, John</hi> 21. 17. And by what St. <hi>John</hi> ſays of him, <hi>he knew all Men;</hi> and again, <hi>he knew what was in Man,</hi> John 2. 24, 25. but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by what our Saviour ſaith of himſelf, <hi>I am he which ſearcheth the Reins and Hearts,</hi> Rev. 2. 23.</p>
               <p>Let us begin with the Words of St. <hi>John,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>knew all Men,</hi> and <hi>knew what was in Man.</hi> The Occaſion of theſe Words will ſhew us their Intent and Meaning; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Perſons upon hearing our Saviour's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and ſeeing his Miracles, believed on him; nevertheleſs, ſaith this Evangeliſt, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus committed not himſelf to them, becauſe he knew all Men, and needed not that any ſhould teſtify of Man, for he knew what was in Man.</hi> As who ſhould ſay, <q>The Lord Chriſt was not free to commit his Perſon or his Secrets to theſe <hi>new</hi> Believers; he did not judg them fit to be truſted till they were well grounded and ſetled in the Faith: he knew what all Men are, how <hi>ſickle</hi> and <hi>uncertain,</hi> nay oft-times <hi>deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>malicious;</hi> ſo he needed not that any ſhould bid him be cautions, or aware of Men: Himſelf knew better than all Men the Infidelity, Treachery, Variableneſs, and all other Infirmities of Men; therefore he would not confide in Perſons not known to him by ſome Experience firſt had of them.</q> This is the natural and obvious Senſe of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Words; they are (very evidently) a Teſtimony of our Saviour's <hi>Prudence</hi> as a Man, not of his <hi>Omniſcience</hi> as a God.</p>
               <p>There is no more Force to Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi>'s Purpoſe in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Words to our Saviour, <hi>Thou knoweſt all things.</hi> The Lord Jeſus had ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> Peter, <hi>lovest thou me? Peter</hi> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that ſuch a Queſtion ſhould be put to him, anſwers, <hi>Lord, thou knowest all things, thou knoweſt I love thee.</hi> His undoubted mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, <hi>There is no Secret hid from thee; thou fore-ſaweſt my Fall, my unhappy Weakneſs in denying thee; but neither is it hid from thee, that I love thee; and then alſo loved thee, though for a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Fear overcame Love.</hi> What is there in this Anſwer to perſwade any reaſonable Man that <hi>Peter</hi> made his Maſter to be God, or believed another, a ſecond God? <hi>Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt all Secrets;</hi> but was not <hi>Peter</hi> aware that it was <hi>by Revelation from God,</hi> by God's inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit or Inſpiration, that our Saviour and ſo many other Prophets knew all the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the Perſons with whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed? Let us ſee whether we cannot even <hi>wrest</hi> it from our Oppoſers, that all our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Knowledg, whether of <hi>Secrets</hi> or of <hi>things to come,</hi> was by Revelation from God; not from his own proper and natural Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as God! St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in his preſent State of Exaltation, has this Paſſage; <hi>Rev. 1. 1. The Revelation of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which God gave to him, to ſhew to his Servants things that muſt ſhortly come to paſs; and he</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>ſent and ſignified it by his Angel</hi> (or by his Meſſenger) <hi>to his Servant</hi> John. What Artifices, what Eluſions or Shifts will Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> betake him to, to get rid of this Text, which indeed putteth an End to the Queſtion of our Saviour's Divinity! For were he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205939:9"/> God, were his Knowledg of all <hi>Secrets</hi> and of <hi>things to come,</hi> from his own Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as God, it could never have been ſaid of him, <hi>the Revelation of Jeſus Christ, which God gave to him, to ſhew to his Servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Oppoſer's laſt Hope is in the Words of our Saviour, <hi>I ſearch the Reins and Heart.</hi> He ought to know, that to <hi>ſearch the Heart and Reins</hi> is an Hebrew and Scripture-Phraſe or Form of ſpeaking, and ſignifies no more but this, <hi>to know the moſt ſecret Thoughts and Purpoſes of the Mind and Heart.</hi> This Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is originally in none but God; but it may be in others derivatively, by Derivation or Revelation from God. Only God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Reins and Heart <hi>originally of himſelf,</hi> or <hi>by his own proper and natural Omniſcience:</hi> but Prophets, and more eſpecially our Saviour, ſearch and know the Hearts, <hi>ſecondarily, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatively, by God's Revelation to them,</hi> or by his inhabiting Spirit in them. We are aſſured, that only this laſt was our Saviour's mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in theſe Words, <hi>I ſearch the Heart;</hi> by the firſt Words of this Book of Revelation, before quoted, even theſe, <hi>the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, which God gave to him.</hi> There could be no need that God ſhould make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation to him, if he himſelf <hi>knew the Reins and Heart</hi> by a natural Omniſcience of his own. In one Word, we ought not to ſtick at the mere Syllables, <hi>I ſearch the Heart,</hi> but ſhould conſider the Import or Senſe of that Phraſe in the Scripture-Language; If it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies only thus much, to know the Thoughts of the Heart or Mind, it will not prove the Perſon, of whom they are ſpoken, to be om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient, or God, unleſs it be alſo ſaid he knoweth the Heart <hi>by his own Omniſcience,</hi> and not (as 'tis ſaid of our Saviour) <hi>by Revelation from God,</hi> or God's inhabiting Spirit.</p>
               <p>The fifth Attribute of God is his <hi>Power;</hi> and this Author fears not to ſay, at <hi>p.</hi> 40. the Lord Chriſt is <hi>as powerful as God.</hi> I marvel that a ſenſible Man could ſay ſuch a thing; for <hi>as powerful as God,</hi> is plainly to ſay, <hi>two</hi> Almighties, and <hi>two</hi> Gods. 'Tis impoſſible for Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> to evade this contradictory and blaſphemous Conſequence, but by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which will be as ſilly as <hi>this</hi> is impious. He cannot eſcape it, but by ſaying, that the Lord Chriſt himſelf is that God; but then, <hi>as powerful as God,</hi> amounts to this, <hi>as powerful as himſelf.</hi> Hath Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> taken a Journey from <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> to bleſs us with ſuch a Diſcovery, that the Lord Chriſt is as powerful as himſelf, or <hi>is as powerful as he is powerful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here too we muſt examine his Proofs; our Saviour ſaith of himſelf, <hi>John 5. 19. What things ſoever the Father doeth, thoſe alſo doeth the Son.</hi> Again he ſaith, <hi>John 6. 40. He that believeth on me, hath eternal Life, and I will raiſe him at the last Day.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of him, Phil. 3. 21. <hi>Who ſhall change our vile Body, that it may be like his glorious Body, according to the Working whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</hi> Laſtly, we have this Argument of our Saviour's Almighty Power, that St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Without him was not any thing made that was made,</hi> John 1. 3. Which thing St. <hi>Paul</hi> dilates more largely in theſe Words; <hi>For by him were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, viſible and inviſible;—all things were created by him and for him,</hi> Col. 1. 16.</p>
               <p>'Tis the perpetual Method, Sir, of our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, to argue from imperfect broken Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Holy Scripture, concealing what goes before, and what follows after; as alſo how thoſe Expreſſions are elſewhere interpreted by the Scriptures themſelves. But the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this is, never ſo little Sincerity in quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Scriptures would ruine their Cauſe. Be you Judg, Sir, whether this be not a juſt Charge: The Lord Chriſt, ſaith Mr. <hi>Lamoth,</hi> is <hi>as powerful as God;</hi> for he himſelf ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever things the Father doeth, thoſe alſo doeth the Son:</hi> but he conceals what goes before in the ſame Verſe, <hi>Verily, verily I ſay to you, the Son can do nothing of himſelf:</hi> And what again follows at <hi>ver. 30. I can do nothing of my ſelf.</hi> He was aware that theſe (explicatory) Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions would deſtroy his Argument from that part of the Verſe which he alledged to prove that our Saviour is <hi>another Almighty:</hi> therefore he was reſolved only to quote the Part of the Verſe, which being ſeparated from the reſt, and repeated by it ſelf, would ſeem to make for his Purpoſe. But if you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205939:10"/> add to theſe Words which he hath diſlocated from the reſt, even to theſe, <hi>What things the Father doeth, thoſe alſo doeth the Son:</hi> I ſay, if to theſe you add, <hi>the Son can do nothing of himſelf;</hi> and again, <hi>I can of my ſelf do nothing;</hi> our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's meaning will be clearly this; <q>The Son raiſeth the Dead, giveth Sight to the Blind, and doth whatſoever elſe of that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Nature that the Father himſelf ſometimes doth; but 'tis with this immenſe Difference, that <hi>the Son can do nothing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> nothing by his own proper Authority or Power, but by the Power and Spirit of the Father dwelling in him, as in former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</q> It is our Saviour himſelf, and after him the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> that make this Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and give this Account of that miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Power of our Saviour, by which he <hi>did whatſoever things the Father doeth.</hi> John 14. 10. <hi>The Father that dwelleth in me, he doeth the Works.</hi> Matth. 12. 28. <hi>I caſt out Devils by the Spirit of God.</hi> Acts 2. 22. <hi>Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>a Man approved of God among you, by Miracles, and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Signs, which God did by him in the midst of you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have ſeen with what Conſcience our Author quotes the Scriptures; I am deſirous to make trial whether his Judgment be no greater than his Sincerity! Thoſe Words of our Saviour which he is ſo deſirous to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal, the Son can do nothing <hi>of himſelf;</hi> and I <hi>of my ſelf</hi> can do nothing: I beſeech you, Sir, <hi>are they the Voice of God,</hi> or of <hi>a Man?</hi> Will he that is true God and Almighty, ſay, I can of my ſelf do nothing; it is by the Power and Authority of another by which I do whatſoever I do!</p>
               <p>Come we to his two next Places, that <hi>Christ will raiſe Believers at the laſt Day,</hi> and that he will <hi>change their vile Bodies, to be like his glorious Body, according to that Power by which he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</hi> I will put a Queſtion to this Gentleman: Doth Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> think that the Lord Chriſt, in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of Exaltation, now raiſes (or <hi>will</hi> raiſe) the Dead, by any other Power but <hi>that</hi> by which he raiſed the Dead while he lived upon Earth? His Hypotheſis will not allow him to ſay that the Lord Chriſt hath now any <hi>greater</hi> or <hi>other</hi> Power than he had while he was upon Earth: It remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that our Lord Chriſt will raiſe the Dead <hi>at the last Day,</hi> by the ſame Power by which he raiſed divers Perſons in his Life-time. But I will demonſtrate to him, that Power was not our Lord's <hi>inherent,</hi> proper or own Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but given to him by God, <hi>pro renatâ,</hi> for the preſent Occaſion, and that too at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or Prayer, or Suit of our Lord Chriſt to God. We ſee <hi>this</hi> very plainly in the caſe of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> whoſe <hi>vile</hi> Body (nay whoſe <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted</hi> Body) was by him <hi>changed</hi> and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Life: For when Jeſus came to the Grave of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to call him forth to Life again, before he ſays, Lazarus <hi>come forth,</hi> he firſt devoutly owns by <hi>whoſe</hi> Power he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed this Miracle; ſee his Words, <hi>John 11. 41. Jeſus lift up his Eyes, and ſaid, Father, I thank thee, that thou haſt heard me: And I knew that thou always heareſt me; but becauſe of the People which ſtand by, I ſay it, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that thou haſt ſent me. When he had thus ſpoken, he cried with a loud Voice,</hi> Lazarus, <hi>come forth.</hi> I am willing, Sir, that our Oppoſers try all their Skill, uſe all their wonted, or any <hi>new</hi> Eluſions, to wreſt this Text out of our Hands. Let them tell us, whether our Saviour doth not here attribute both his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority of raiſing this dead Perſon, to only the Prevalence of his Prayers with God, who <hi>always</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>heareth me.</hi> Let them tell us, if they dare, and if it deſtroys not their Hypotheſis; that now however, in his State of Exaltation, the Lord Chriſt hath <hi>a new</hi> Power; and that he ſhall raiſe the Dead, not as while he was upon Earth, by <hi>an extraordinary</hi> Power conferred on him by God, (who hath ſometimes given the ſame Power to dead and dry Bones, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. 21.) but by a Power <hi>newly</hi> grown up in himſelf.</p>
               <p>To the Text of St. <hi>John</hi> concerning the WORD, <hi>without him was not any thing made that was made;</hi> I have largely ſhown in the <hi>5th Chapter</hi> of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn,</hi> that the Evangeliſt is there ſpeaking of <hi>the new Creation,</hi> or the Goſpel-Oeconomy and State of things, not of the outward, viſible, or material Creation or World. If Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205939:10"/> will ſatisfy the Reaſons alledged in that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the Socinians will be indebted to him for ever.</p>
               <p>But he urges us, in the laſt Place, with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, <hi>Col. 1. 16. For by him were all things created, in Heaven and in Earth, viſible and inviſible; all things were created by him and for him.</hi> It muſt be confeſs'd that this Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath but one Fault. In the Judgment of all the Criticks and Interpreters of Note, of our Author's own Party, <hi>'tis moſt falſly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> they read the Text after this manner, <hi>for by him</hi> (by the Lord Chriſt) <hi>were all things modelled that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, viſible and inviſible; they were all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled by him, and for him.</hi> The <hi>inviſible</hi> Powers of Heaven, even the Angelical Orders, and the State of Affairs upon Earth (more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of the Church) have undergone a very great Change, have been modelled, and as it were <hi>new-made</hi> by the Lord Chriſt. On Earth he hath aboliſhed Paganiſm, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Superſtition, and introduced in their room the Knowledg of the one true God, and a moral Righteouſneſs. In Heaven the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelic Orders are put under his Directions, and by him engaged in the Defence of the Church, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14. Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> may ſee in the fourth Letter of the <hi>Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> how many learned Perſons (Fathers and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns) of his own Party, have thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood this Text: They plainly ſaw, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks here of the new Creation, not of the original making, but the modelling or new-making of things: and I cannot think it neceſſary further to anſwer Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi> upon this Text, till he has ſatisfied the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Judicious and Learned of his own Party.</p>
               <p>The laſt Attribute to evince that the Lord Chriſt is equal with God, is his <hi>Mercy.</hi> Our Author ſaith, Chriſt's Mercy is ſufficient to demonſtrate him to be true God. His Proof of this is, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo commonly wiſhes <hi>Grace and Peace to the Churches, from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi> He ſaith at <hi>p.</hi> 43. An Apoſtle would be <hi>better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed</hi> than to wiſh them <hi>Grace</hi> from any other but only God: the Scriptures he ſaith, <hi>never tell us</hi> of the Grace of Angels or of Men. He advances another Example of his Ignorance or his Forgetfulneſs, when he tells us, that 'tis ſaid by our Saviour to the Diſciples, <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize all Nations in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>There are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> but in the Scriptures nothing that is <hi>created</hi> is made to go hand in hand with God, or is reckoned in the ſame Line or Period with him. He adds further, but the Lord Chriſt is (in ſome Texts) not only reckoned with God, but is <hi>ſet before him,</hi> as in thoſe Words of St. <hi>Paul, The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Love of God, the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt be with you;</hi> therefore without doubt he is true God. Can we imagine, ſaith this wary and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author, <hi>that the Scriptures would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch an Abſurdity,</hi> if the Son were no more than a Creature?</p>
               <p>He is a pretty Gentleman; and ſeeing his Superiours have not thought fit to reſtrain his Extravagancies, 'tis neceſſary that his Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, who has the next Right, ſhould. He is poſitive that Creatures are <hi>never</hi> ſet in the ſame Line or Context of Words and Senſe with God, much leſs are ſet before him; and that Grace is <hi>never</hi> wiſhed to the Churches from any but God. Now in his Hypotheſis, the Lord Chriſt is God; therefore let him take his Bible, and find there this Text; Rev. 1. 4, 5. John <hi>to the ſeven Churches which are in</hi> Aſia, <hi>Grace be to you, and Peace, from him which is, and which was, and which is to come; and from the ſeven Spirits which are before his Throne, and from Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Here Grace is wiſhed from <hi>the ſeven Spirits of the Preſence,</hi> and theſe are reckoned in the ſame Context of Words and Senſe with God, and are ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before our Saviour, who according to our Author, is true God. Nay, and the Author of this manner of ſpeaking is St. <hi>John, that</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> on whom Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> hath beſtowed ſome Pulpit-Rhetorick, telling us at <hi>p.</hi> 38. <q>Let us make no Scruple to believe <hi>the beloved Diſciple,</hi> who repoſed himſelf on the Breaſt of the Son of God: Truſt we to the piercing Sight of <hi>this Eagle,</hi> who took a View of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205939:11"/> this glorious Sun; Let us rely on the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Evangeliſt, whoſe very End in writing his Goſpel was to prove that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God.</q> With more ſuch <hi>Pedantry,</hi> which however he taketh to be <hi>Wit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To what he ſaith concerning the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Christ; and the Concluſion.</head>
               <p>WE are near our Deliverance from his Impertinencies: for at <hi>p.</hi> 44. he begins to ſpeak to the laſt Argument of three, by which he undertook (at firſt) to prove our Saviour's Divinity, which is that <hi>he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</hi> He ſaith here, that <hi>Worſhip is</hi> (as it were) <hi>the Shadow of the Godhead;</hi> let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſaith he, <hi>thereby take the Height and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Saviour.</hi> I ſhewed this Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a Friend of mine, asking him, what might be the meaning of it, or in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <hi>Worſhip is (as it were) the Shadow of the Godhead?</hi> He ſaid, that I underſtood very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; for this is one of the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians, which muſt be believed with an humble and implicit Faith, and not ſaucily pried into or enquired after. For all that I was of Opinion, that it hapned here to Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi> as to other Orators and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Men, who when they come to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End of a Diſcourſe, having well near ſpent their Embelliſhments and Flouriſhes, they fill up the vacant Spaces with a curious Mixture of <hi>Flouriſh</hi> and <hi>Nonſenſe.</hi> Worſhip is (as it were) <hi>the Shadow of the Godhead:</hi> there's <hi>the Nonſenſe;</hi> Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> himſelf will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, upon ſecond Thoughts, to be pure Nonſenſe. But then, <hi>let us thereby take the Height and Elevation of our Saviour;</hi> there's <hi>the Flouriſh,</hi> Decoration or Gild with which to cover it from Fools.</p>
               <p>For the reſt; Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> not having urged any thing from Scripture or Reaſon, for <hi>the Worſhip</hi> of our Saviour, but only what had been before ſaid by Mr. <hi>Milbourn,</hi> to whom I have anſwered (ſo far as concerneth this Part of our Conteſt) at <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to him. I will paſs now from the <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative</hi> Parts of his Book to the <hi>hiſtorical;</hi> for he hath obliged us with the Hiſtory of a new French Synod, held at <hi>London</hi> by ninety ſix French Divines, <hi>March</hi> 30, 1691.</p>
               <p>He gives us the Reſult and Concluſions of this either Synod or <hi>Riot</hi> (for it aſſembled by no <hi>legal</hi> Authority, and the Aſſiſtants at it are puniſhable by our Laws) in ſeven decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory Propoſitions; which ſeven Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may however be reduced to theſe two, that <hi>the French Miniſters are no Socinians,</hi> and that <hi>they are no Presbyterians.</hi> The firſt of theſe Declarations is wholly <hi>ridiculous;</hi> the other is equally <hi>ſurprizing</hi> and <hi>unadviſed;</hi> I will diſpatch with both in two Words.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The French Miniſters are no Socinians: Bleſs me! who ever ſaid they were? Such as know the French Miniſters, know very well that they are ſo far from being Socinians, that they never rightly underſtood what Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm is; they are ſo perfectly ignorant of the Merits of the Socinian Cauſe and Queſtions, that 'tis notoriouſly known, they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant enough in good Books, to diſtinguiſh Socinianiſm from Remonſtrantiſm: A Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian and a Remonſtrant are convertible Terms with the Generality of the French Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Thence it is that their Brethren in <hi>Holland</hi> count the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Socinians, becauſe they are generally Remonſtrants; and thoſe Refugee Miniſters who have joined in Communion with them, to be like as they are, unſound in the Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They add, the French Miniſters are (now) no Presbyterians. A fooliſh and a raſh Declaration: What needed they to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim to all the Presbyteries here and abroad, that ſince their coming into <hi>England, they have turned their Coats?</hi> Was it worth their while to diſown ſo publickly (as well as ſo cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly and raſhly) the original Diſcipline of their Church?</p>
               <p>Let us hear how they have worded their <hi>famous Recantation;</hi> 
                  <q>We <hi>heartily</hi> ſubſcribe to the Confeſſion of <hi>Faith</hi> of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> without pretending to meddle with Matter of Diſcipline.</q> They take here <hi>a civil Leave</hi> of Presbyterianiſm, and in <hi>a Meioſis,</hi> renounce the half of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205939:11"/> at once: <hi>We meddle not with Matters of Diſcipline,</hi> that is, as we heartily profeſs the Points of <hi>Faith</hi> of our Churches, ſo we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh <hi>the Diſcipline</hi> of the ſame: They were not willing <hi>to anathematize</hi> the Presbytery, <hi>that</hi> had been ſomewhat too rigid for <hi>new</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners and <hi>young</hi> Epiſcoparians. <hi>But we med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with it;</hi> we let it go in God's Name, to ſhift for it ſelf, for we will be no longer concerned <hi>with</hi> it, or <hi>for</hi> it. I hope Mr. <hi>Quick</hi> will inſert the Decrees of this <hi>London</hi>-Synod into his <hi>Synodicon Galliae reformatae;</hi> that the World may know, that the French Miniſters, to their other Vertues, have added alſo that of the Age, <hi>to temporize.</hi> Nor am I ſo much their Enemy, but that I wiſh them ſome Fruit of ſo great a Complaiſance to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the giving up to her, at once, <hi>the Moiety</hi> of their Religion.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> hath acquainted the World, what the French Miniſters <hi>are not;</hi> I cannot reſtrain my ſelf from declaring what ſome of them (too many) <hi>are:</hi> They are Peepers, Lurchers and Trapans; they skulk about the Preſſes, Bookſellers Shops, and even at pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſes, to get Informations about <hi>unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed</hi> Books, and <hi>heterodox</hi> Opinions and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: They are Informers, not only in the Houſes of Biſhops, (who diſdain at it) but in the Courts of Judicature, to the indelible and perpetual Scandal of their miniſterial Function, as well as the Trouble and Danger of the Perſons whom they illegally inform againſt, and proſecute for Matters of <hi>mere</hi> Conſcience and Religion, or rather for their Love of Peace, and Deſire of Catholick U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Among the reſt there is one Monſieur (I will conceal his Name for this once, but 'tis very like to) <hi>Hocus,</hi> who is excellent at the Diſcovery of an Heterodox Book, and at pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Author before <hi>the Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Judg, and then before <hi>the Civil.</hi> He is ſo brisk and <hi>home</hi> an Informer, that 'tis enough with him if a Book hath nothing <hi>directly</hi> hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox, but only ſpeaketh leſs conſiderately and adviſedly, and ſo may have an Heterodox or <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Conſtruction put upon it: But withal he is ſo <hi>ſneakingly</hi> falſe, that while he is informing and ſetting the Officers at work to apprehend, he will very ſolemnly deny that he was the Mover of this Trouble. If he and his Fraternity would not be further expoſed, not only here, but in <hi>France,</hi> where they will be glad to hear <hi>the evil Report</hi> of the French Miniſters; they will for the time to come take ſome honeſter Courſe to recommend themſelves to the ſmall Gratuities which they may expect from ſuch Services; Services that are odious (I can aſſure them) to thoſe very Perſons for whoſe Intereſts they are done. I will conclude with minding them of two things; that 'tis dangerous for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Men to irritate a whole Party by Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there being no <hi>Party</hi> that can be called ſmall or weak. And next, that if they find themſelves harſhly anſwered in this Reply to Mr. <hi>Lamoth,</hi> let them remember that they have given us an inſufferable Provocation, there being nothing ſo intolerable as that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugees for Conſcience, ſhould turn Informers and Perſecutors for Matters purely conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for mere Diſſent in Points of Faith.</p>
               <p>But I have done with them for this time: If hereafter Mr. <hi>Lamoth,</hi> or any others, ſhall think fit to ingage in theſe Controverſies, and can forbear reproachful Reflections on a whole Party, keeping themſelves to Matter of Argument, and to the Miſtakes of this particular Defendant, they ſhall be anſwered <hi>accordingly.</hi> I will reply as ſhall become a Chriſtian and a Gentleman; I will as little be guilty of Diſreſpect, without a notorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation in the ſame kind, as I will quarrel with a Perſon that informs me of my Way, when he perceives I am out of it. I need add no more now, but that, Sir, I receive reſpectfully the large and ſurprizing Favours you have done to</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged and moſt Aſſured, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:205939:12"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Send you herewith the Anſwer of one of our Friends, to the two Diſcourſes of Mr. <hi>Lamoth,</hi> concerning the Divinity of our Saviour; if you ſend it to the Preſs, I pray let this preſent Supplement go along with it. For having ſeen the Articles of ſome French Miniſters, exhibited at the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Court of my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>L.</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>A. L.</hi> at firſt I admired at the Impertinence, the Boldneſs and Malice of their Undertaking; but afterwards I thought alſo it might be fit to take this Occaſion, to mind them of ſome things, of which (I am perſwaded) they have never duly thought.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Place they have dared to article againſt a Perſon, in an Eccleſiaſtical Court, contrary to the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of a <hi>Statute</hi> or <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament: For the late Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning Toleration and Indulgence in Matters of Conſcience and Religion, granted to Socinians as well as other Proteſtants the Benefit of that Act, except only in Caſe that they ſhall <hi>print</hi> or <hi>preach</hi> in Defence and Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of their Opinions. The Socinians are as much tolerated and favoured by that <hi>Act</hi> as any other Sect of Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if they content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to hold their Opinions, or to reaſon and diſcourſe of them in familiar Talk; the <hi>Act</hi> debarreth us from only the Liberty of <hi>Preaching</hi> or <hi>Writing</hi> in favour of them. But now the Perſon againſt whom the French Miniſters article, hath committed no ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; they do not ſo much as pretend that he has <hi>written</hi> or <hi>preach'd</hi> againſt the received Doctrine of the Church: theſe Miniſters therefore are guilty of an Inſult upon the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Laws, and the Statutes of our Kings and Parliaments; and are liable to a Proſecution thereupon in the Civil Courts, by the Perſons whom they have particularly wronged, or by any other <hi>publick-ſpirited</hi> Perſons, to whom the Liberties of the Nation are dear. They may happen to find ſome not obſcure Perſons, who in due Place and Time will make the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſenſible, that 'tis not for <hi>Refugees</hi> to trample upon the Laws of the Country where they are received and protected; and leaſt of all upon thoſe Laws which were made and deſigned for the Eaſe and Peace of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and on which the Welfare and Safety of the Nation do much depend.</p>
            <p>But the Perſon, it ſhould ſeem, againſt whom they article, hath no need of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief from the Act of Indulgence; he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by the Miniſters as a Socinian, only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he is not a Sabellian,</hi> and becauſe <hi>he holds the Neceſſity of good Works.</hi> They article, that he hath (<hi>malitiouſly and wickedly</hi>) affirmed, ſpeaking concerning the Bleſſed Trinity, that he could clearly prove, that <hi>three are not one,</hi> and that <hi>one and two are three.</hi> He anſwers, that he meant thereby, that <hi>three Perſons are not one Perſon;</hi> that is, he is no Sabellian, he believeth the real Diſtinction of the Perſons, or as the Athanaſian Creed ſaith, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeth not the Perſons. They article, that he hath (<hi>malitiouſly and heretically</hi>) ſaid, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt hath merited nothing for us,</hi> and that <hi>he hath but done what he was obliged to do; or Words to that effect.</hi> He anſwers, that his Words were not to that Effect; the true and whole meaning of his Words was only this, that the Merit and Satisfaction of the Lord Chriſt is to be ſo interpreted, as not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, ſuperſede or diſpenſe with <hi>good Works of our own,</hi> that is to ſay, a holy Life on our Part. This <hi>indeed</hi> is to be no Calviniſt; but for all that, 'tis neither Hereſy nor Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm; but it ſerves to confirm what our Friend hath ſaid in his Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Lamoth,</hi> that 'tis notoriouſly known, that the French Miniſters underſtand not what Socinianiſm is, and that they confound Socinianiſm with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſm or Remonſtrantiſm. I am ſorry for this ſame honeſt Dr. <hi>A. L.</hi> becauſe though it appears by theſe and the reſt of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, that he is no Socinian, yet he is for <hi>the Neceſſity of Holineſs,</hi> a good Life, or good Works; which Doctrine was ever ſo diſpleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> and his Followers, the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205939:12"/> French Miniſters, that ſometimes they deny there is any ſuch thing as good Works; and otherwhile they affirm, that good Works are not only no neceſſary Conditions of Salvation, but are even pernitious, dangerous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive thereof. They are ſo much of this Mind, that they make the contrary Doctrine to be <hi>Hereſy;</hi> and becauſe they think they cannot any way render it more odious, they call it <hi>Socinianiſm;</hi> but I adviſe them, ſeeing Popery is now ſo much abominated in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that they would rather call it <hi>Jeſuitiſm;</hi> they ſhould have proſecuted this Dr. <hi>A. L.</hi> as <hi>a Jeſuit</hi> rather than as a Socinian; that had been a way to ſet <hi>the Rabble,</hi> as well as the Spiritual Court, upon him.</p>
            <p>But if Socinianiſm and the Engliſh Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are indeed ſuch Eye-ſores to theſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as ſeems by their frequent Proſecutions of divers Perſons on that Account before the Eccleſiaſtical Judges, and in other Courts, they ſhould at leaſt have ſhewn ſo much Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as not to miſplace their Accuſations, ſo groſly too, as they have done. This Dr. <hi>A. L.</hi> is the fourth or fifth Perſon to whom they have given a Publick Trouble, on the Account of Socinianiſm: they have been always baffled, and ſometimes ſeverely check'd by the Judges and Court; all this has not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them, they having no Reputation to loſe, from renewing their <hi>Perſecutions</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Perſons. But I adviſe them much, to lay the Saddle upon the right Horſe; and let them not ſo wholly deſpiſe the Imputations of Calumny and Malice, Vices ſo unſutable to their Profeſſion of Miniſters: Let them ceaſe to accuſe thoſe that are not guilty, when they may eaſily find ſo many who are not only guilty of Unitarianiſm, if it be a Guilt, but are alſo <hi>liable</hi> upon that Account; my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, have <hi>preach'd</hi> up and <hi>written</hi> for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarianiſm. They have, for Inſtance, the <hi>four</hi> Evangeliſts and the Apoſtles, notoriouſly guilty of the Hereſy now called Socinianiſm; and their Words are ſo clear and expreſs for it, that the Miniſters need not fear the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Slander, if they ſhall article a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them at the Places and Courts where they have lately libelled Dr. <hi>L.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gr.</hi> If the Reader will pardon me, and not abate of his due Reverence, I will be content to prepare the Articles for the Miniſters, in their own Forms and Terms; they ſhall have no other Trouble but what they ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and like, even to exhibit them in the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſtiled Apoſtle; and you <hi>Mark,</hi> called an Evangeliſt, have <hi>mal. and wic.</hi> complotted together, to <hi>teach and write</hi> the Hereſy which denieth <hi>the Omniſcience</hi> of the Son our Lord Chriſt, while you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and <hi>publiſhed,</hi> as from the Mouth of Chriſt himſelf, that <hi>the Son knoweth not the Time of the laſt Judgment;</hi> and that <hi>only the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (whom all Men grant not to be the Son) <hi>knoweth of that Day,</hi> Mat. 24. 36. Mark 13. 32.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You <hi>John,</hi> calling your ſelf Evangeliſt and Apoſtle, have not ſpared to <hi>write</hi> and <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> ſcandalous, heretical and blaſp. Words againſt the <hi>Omnipotence</hi> of the ſame our Lord Chriſt, affirming moſt injuriouſly and falſly, that <hi>he can do nothing of himſelf:</hi> and further, that it was <hi>not be, but the Father dwelling in him, that did all the miraculous Works.</hi> So you have ſaid expreſly, <hi>John 5. 19, 30. John</hi> 14. 10. With which monſtrous Doctrine you <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> alſo ſymbolized when you <hi>preached</hi> to the Jews concerning the Lord Chriſt: for thus you ſay of him; <hi>Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>a Man approved of God among you, by Miracles and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Signs, which God did by him,</hi> Acts 2. 22. Et objicimus &amp; articulamur ut ſupra.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You the ſaid <hi>John, not having the Fear of—before your Eyes,</hi> but led by an heretical and blaſp. Spirit, have <hi>written</hi> and <hi>publiſhed,</hi> and as from the Mouth of our Saviour, that <hi>the Father is greater than he,</hi> John 14. 28. To which Hereſy you <hi>Paul</hi> have conſented, when you do write to the Corinthians, that <hi>the Head of the Woman is the Man, and the Head of Chriſt is God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 3. But the divine <hi>Athanaſius</hi> hath in his Creed expreſly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted you.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And further, you <hi>John</hi> have <hi>written and publiſhed</hi> Words, in which 'tis evident that you deſigning to deny <hi>the ſupreme Authority</hi> of the Son our Lord Chriſt; for you make him to ſay, that <hi>he came not of himſelf, but as ſent by the Father,</hi> and that <hi>his Doctrine was not his own, but the Father's that ſent him;</hi> and that <hi>as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205939:13"/> the Father had commanded him, ſo in all things ſpake he;</hi> John 8. 42. John 8. 28. John 12. 49.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You <hi>Luke,</hi> called alſo an Evangeliſt, have been yet more audacious; you have <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed</hi> to the World, that the Lord Chriſt was not only <hi>not God,</hi> but that he needed to be ſtrengthned in his Agonies before his Paſſion by an Angel, and that he prayed earneſtly to God; as if he who was himſelf God, and the only true God, could need the Aid of an Angel, or to make Prayer to any whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. The others, your Companions in this Hereſy, have with ſome Modeſty contented themſelves to deny our Saviour's <hi>Omnipotence;</hi> but you have repreſented him, as in ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, <hi>impotent</hi> and <hi>weak,</hi> Luke 22. 43, 44.</p>
            <p n="6">6. All of you, jointly and ſeverally, have ſpoken of God by only the ſingular Pronouns, <hi>I, Thou, Me, Him, Himſelf, Thy ſelf,</hi> and ſuch like; which Pronouns are never uſed in any Language but only of one ſingle Perſon, not of more Perſons; and hereby you have fully aſſured us, that your Belief is, that there is but one Perſon of God, not three Perſons, or a Trinity of Perſons. But you <hi>Paul</hi> have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to ſay, even in Terms, that God is but one Perſon: for you write to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, that <hi>the Son is</hi> (what, God? No, but) <hi>the Image of God's Perſon,</hi> Heb. 1. 3.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To leave no Place for doubt, you <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> have expreſly <hi>taught</hi> and <hi>publiſhed,</hi> that <hi>only the Father is true God;</hi> and him you make to be even <hi>the God of the Son,</hi> or the God whom the Son worſhippeth and ſerveth: You have ſaid and written, <hi>Father,—This is Life eternal, to know thee (the only true God) and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent:</hi> or, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt thy Meſſenger.</hi> And again; <hi>To us there is but one God, the Father:—and one Lord</hi> (or one <hi>Maſter,</hi> that is, Teacher) <hi>Jeſus Christ.</hi> And you <hi>Paul,</hi> above all others, have incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and repeated this Doctrine: You tell the Corinthians, that <hi>Chriſt ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to God, even the Father.</hi> And you adviſe the Romans, <hi>that with one Mouth they ſhould glorify God, even the Father.</hi> Plainly, as if only the Father were God; <hi>John 17. 1, 3. 1 Cor. 8. 6. 1 Cor. 15. 24. Rom.</hi> 15. 6.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To burden you at preſent with no more; All of you, jointly and ſeverally, have in ſuch manner diſtinguiſhed between God and the Lord Chriſt, that your way of ſpeaking amounts to a plain Denial, that the Lord Chriſt is God. You make our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſay to the young Man whom he loved, <hi>Why calleſt thou me Good? there is none Good ſave one, that is God.</hi> You ſay, <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> You exhort, <hi>Let every Tongue confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord</hi> (Gr. that the Lord Jeſus is the Chriſt) <hi>to the Glory of God, the Father.</hi> You cry out, <hi>To God only Wiſe be Glory, through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> You have taught, that <hi>the Son ſhall be ſubject to him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all;</hi> Luke 18. 19. 1 Tim. 2. 5. Phil. 2. 11. Rom. 16. 27. 1 Cor. 15. 28. If we put all theſe Expreſſions together, you are found to deny the Omniſcience, the Omnipotence, and the ſupreme Authority of the Lord Chriſt: and in ſome Caſes you make him to be even im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and weak; and having thus diveſted him, as much as in you lies, of all the Grand Characters and Attributes of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, you add, that God is but one Perſon, and that this one Perſon is only the Father, and that Chriſt is a Man, whom we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways carefully diſtinguiſh from God.</p>
            <p>Thus it is, and theſe are the Men againſt whom the French Miniſters (in purſuance of their Principles) ſhould have articled, in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts: theſe are the true Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, and Fathers of Unitarianiſm, on whom the Blame and Charge ſhould light. 'Tis in vain for the Miniſters to rail at, and be <hi>Informers</hi> (in a ſtrange Land) againſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Unitarian Books and Perſons, unleſs they can firſt get the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, and their Writings ſuppreſs'd. But in preſenting the Articles, I would have Mr. <hi>Lamoth</hi> be Foreman, becauſe they are ſuted to his Doctrine. I need not, Sir, add any more; I am of Opinion that the Miniſters, for one while, may have enough of this.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am your Aſſured,</salute>
               <signed>E. E.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:205939:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
